<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Truth may be blam'd but not sham'd a sermon upon Matth. 16 v.13, 14, 15, 16 : wherein truth and errour are brought upon the stage act their parts / by William Harvey, minister of the Word.</title>
            <author>Harvey, William, minister of the Word.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1657</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 50 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 23 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A43041</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H1094</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R36593</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">15736146</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 15736146</idno>
            <idno type="VID">104571</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A43041)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 104571)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1593:61)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Truth may be blam'd but not sham'd a sermon upon Matth. 16 v.13, 14, 15, 16 : wherein truth and errour are brought upon the stage act their parts / by William Harvey, minister of the Word.</title>
                  <author>Harvey, William, minister of the Word.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 5-45 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for the authour,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1657.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imperfect: stained, with print show-through and loss of print.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Trinity College Library, Cambridge University.</note>
                  <note>Includes bibliographical references.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Matthew XVI, 13-16 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:104571:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>TRUTH May be blam'd, but not ſham'd. A SERMON Upon Matth. 16. v. 13, 14, 15, 16.</p>
            <p>Wherein Truth and Errour are brought upon the Stage acting their parts, By <hi>WILLIAM HARVEY, Miniſter of the Word.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <p>O fooliſh Galatians, who hath bewitched you that you ſhould not obey the Truth, &amp;c.</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Gal. 3.1.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>Am I therefore become your enemy becauſe I tell you the truth.</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Chap. 4.16.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>Quid de quoquo viro, &amp; cui dicas ſaepe caveto.</q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for the Authour, 1657.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="modern_bookplate">
            <pb facs="tcp:104571:2"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <head>Collegium S. Set Individuce Trinitatis in Academia Cantabrigienſi</head>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:104571:2"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Matth. 16 Chap. verſ. 13, 14, 15, 16.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>When Jeſues came into the coaſts of Ceſarea Philippi, he asked his diſciples, ſaying, Whom do men ſay that I the Son of man am? And they ſaid, So me ſay that thou art John the Baptiſt, ſome Elias, and others Jeremias, or one of the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets. He ſaith unto them, but whom ſay ye that I am? and Simon Peter anſwered and ſaid, Thou art Chriſt the Son of the Living God.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N theſe words we have two queſtions with their anſwers: The queſtions are one and the ſame, but the anſwers are diſtinct and different, accoring to the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent Spirits of the Common people and of the Apoſtles, Both reſpond as they thought, and as their genious prompt them. The Apoſtles give in the judgement of the vulgar, which is various and divers; and they in
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:104571:3"/>the perſon of <hi>Peter</hi> (wrapt as it were in the Clouds) and their tongues touched with a Coal from the altar; give in theirs, <hi>viz.</hi> Thou art Chriſt the Son of the living God. But firſt let us come to the plebeans and hear what opinions the vulgar had of our Saviour. We have them in the thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teenth and fourteenth verſes, Some ſay that thou art <hi>John</hi> the <hi>Baptiſt,</hi> Some <hi>Elias,</hi> and others <hi>Jeremias,</hi> or one of the Prophets. To omit all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Circumſtances of time and place, where and when; The external im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulſive cauſe or occaſion of the giving in of the peoples judgement, was our Lords interrogation; whom do men ſay that I the ſon of man am? Or as S. <hi>Mark</hi> hath it, whom do men ſay that I am? Chap. 8. verſ. 27. Or as S. <hi>Luke;</hi> whom ſay the people that I am. Chap. 9. verſ. 18. By Son of man, Chriſt meant himſelf; which word is uſual in Scripture, and is expreſſed by the Prophet <hi>Daniel,</hi> chap. 7. v. 13. I ſaw in the night viſions, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold one like the Son of man came with the Clouds of heaven, and came
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:104571:3"/>to the antient of dayes, and they brought him neer before him. And all this, to intimate, and point unto us that he was born man of the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> in all things like unto us, (Sin only excepted) as the Apoſtle hath it Heb. 2. chap. verſ. 14, The end of his interrogation, or que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, was not ſiniſter, as affecting popular applauſe, or vain glory; neither was it, becauſe he was igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant of the peoples thoughts of him; For he needed not that any ſhould teſtifie of man, for he knew what was in man. <hi>John</hi> 2. chap. verſ. 25. But hearing the various conceits of the inconſtant people, he might the more fully and rightly inform them in the ſame. The anſwer of the Apoſtles is fourfold, a many headed Hidra, which they give in the name of the Common people; Some ſay that thou. are <hi>John</hi> the <hi>Baptiſt,</hi> ſome <hi>Elias,</hi> and others <hi>Jeremias</hi> or one of the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets. Now, <hi>John</hi> was a notable Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctour, a man for holineſſe of life,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:104571:4"/>innocency, and ſharpneſs in his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proofs above all in his time. This <hi>John, Herod</hi> (not long before) cauſeth to be put to death. Our Lord treading in his ſteps, and exceeding him in inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceney, auſterity in reproving of Sin, and vehemency in his reprehenſions; the Common people conceited, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded themſelves, that he was very <hi>John</hi> the <hi>Baptist,</hi> riſen again from the dead; ſo <hi>Luke</hi> chap. 9. verſ. 7. Becauſe it was ſaid of ſome that <hi>John</hi> was riſen from the dead. With which fond opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion <hi>Herod</hi> himſelf was big, <hi>Matth</hi> 14.2. This is <hi>John</hi> the <hi>Baptiſt,</hi> he is riſen from the dead, therefore mighty works do ſhew forth themſelves in him. Others took him for <hi>Elias,</hi> that noble and he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roick prophet, in the time of king, <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hab</hi> and <hi>Jezabel,</hi> who ſlew the prophets of <hi>Baal,</hi> ſmote the waters of Jordan, and poſſed over as on dry ground, and as too good for earth, is carried in a fiery Charet to heaven, 2 Kings 2.11. Thus we read Mark 6.15. Others ſaid, that it is <hi>Elias,</hi> &amp;c. The ground of this miſtake is the words in <hi>Malachi,</hi> 4. chap. 5. verſe. Behold I will ſend you <hi>Elijah</hi>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:104571:4"/>the prophet before the coming of the great and dreadful day of the Lord. The Jews hereupon falſly imagined our Saviour to be that Tiſhbite come from heaven, and ſo that propheſie of the prophet accompliſhed. Thirdly others again, think him to be <hi>Jeremias,</hi> a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet who was not onely ordained from his mothers womb to preach and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſy to the people; hut the whole courſe of this life was a free reprehend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ſins and enormities of the times. He propheſied the deſtruction of the Temple and the captivity of the Jewes in Babylon. A ſad Omen to as ſad a conſequence, which they found too true by ſad experience. Chriſt therefore with the like zeal reprehending the prieſts, and foreſhewing the deſtruction of the Temple, and Jeruſalem it ſelf, that moſt populous and flouriſhing Citie; hence they blindly ſurmiſe him to be <hi>Jeremias.</hi> Laſtly, others, without poſitive affirming him to be this or that particular, ſhoot their bol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, and blindly ſay that he is one of the prophets. So we read <hi>Luke</hi> 7.16. And there came a fear on all, and they glorified God, ſaying, that a great pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:104571:5"/>is riſen among us, and that God hath viſited his people. And <hi>Luke</hi> 9.8. And, of ſome that <hi>Elias</hi> had appeared, and of others that one of the old pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets was riſen again. And <hi>John</hi> 6.14. This is of a truth that prophet that ſhould come into the world. And thus you have the ſeveral and promiſcuous judgements of the people, concerning our bleſſed Lord. All give in their ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dict, but rove at random, and miſſe the white. Yet the Commons, although they err'd, and (and to uſe <hi>Chryſoſtoms</hi> words) <hi>multo humilior quam opporteba<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eorum de Chriſto erat opinio, a nequitia ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men libera erat;</hi> their opinion concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Chriſt was far beneath him: not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding it was without tincture of wickedneſs. On the contrary, the opinion of the Phariſees ſavour'd of much malice; For they ſaid, he was a Samaritan, and had a devil, and did eject devils through Beelz bub the prince of the devils <hi>Luke</hi> the 11<hi rend="sup">th</hi> 15. <hi>John</hi> 8.48. And ſo I come to the Obſervations in the Text.</p>
            <p>Firſt then, it were not amiſs after the example of our Saviour, when he ſaid,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:104571:5"/>whom do men ſay that I the Son of man am? for us (upon occaſion) to queſtion, and enquire what others ſpeak of us; to underſtand the ſeveral vo'es of the people, and to hear their reſolves; that ſo we may take off all occaſions of ſcandals in time, and opportunely ſtop Calumnies wide and foul mouth. Eſpecially this concerns the Miniſters of Gods word, having more Curs barking at them then any other, <hi>Fama proxima vitae,</hi> a mans fame is next to his life. And the Wife man ſaith, A good name is rather to be cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen then great riches. <hi>Prov.</hi> 22.1. Yet ſee how flyes ſeek to marre theſe preti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ointments, and rob a man of that which is of more value then all the gold of India.<note n="a" place="margin">Si actum de nomine, actum de homine.</note> For, if a mans name be done, he is in a manner undone. S. <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtine</hi> ſaid well;<note n="b" place="margin">Nobis ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſaria eſe vitanoſtra, alils ſama noſtra.</note> Our life is neceſſary for our ſelves, our fame for others. Wherefore tender is as the Apple of thine eye; For as it is ſaid of <hi>Titus,</hi> that he was <hi>delicium humani generis,</hi> the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light and darling of mankinde;<note place="margin">De bon. viduit.</note> ſo is a good name of man, his darling, his delight. <hi>Haec ſunt ornamenta mea</hi> ſaid <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>melia</hi>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:104571:6"/>to a Matron of Campania, point<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to her Sons: Theſe are my jewels, my ornaments. Such a jewel is ones good name to him. My adviſe then is this, take away the cauſe of ſcandal, baſe life and ſinful courſes, and the ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect will ceaſe of it ſelf.<note n="c" place="margin">Da ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ram ut re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cte agas, atque ſio perfrueris hona fama.</note> A good life cannot want a good name. Wherefore as <hi>Epictetus</hi> hath it, Endeavour to do well, and ſo ſhalt thou enjoy a good name. It is ſin that cauſeth ſhame; Rake a dunghil, and it will ſtink. What comes from a fog, but unſavoury ſmels?<note place="margin">Iſaiah 57.20, 21.</note> The wicked are like the troubled Sea, when it cannot reſt, whoſe waters caſt up mire and dirt, There is no peace ſaith my God to the wicked. No peace within their Conſciences, none without, in the thoughts and accepti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the world. Take the moral of this. <hi>Progne,</hi> king <hi>Pandions</hi> daughter, and wife to king <hi>Thereus;</hi> deſired her husband to fetch her ſiſter <hi>Philomela</hi> to her. To be ſhort the fair maid is raviſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by <hi>Thereus,</hi> and her tongue cut out. Coming to her ſiſter, with her needle, (though ſhe could not ſpeak) opens all <hi>Thereus</hi> his villany. <hi>Progne</hi> in revenge
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:104571:6"/>of this foul act, murders her only ſon, and preſents him as a diſh of meat to her husband. This being done; the king riſeth in a rage, whilſt <hi>Progne</hi> makes her eſcape: and the Fable ſaith, <hi>Thereus</hi> was turned into a Lapwing, <hi>Progne</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a Swallow with a ſpot of red on her breaſt, to expreſſe her cruelty, and <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomola</hi> into a Nightingal, as one alwayes bewailing her misfortune. The raviſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing king had theſe verſes of him,
<q>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Rex fueram, fie criſta probat, ſed ſordida vita</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Immundam e tanto culmine ſecit avem.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>This Tuft doth ſhow that once I was a King,</l>
                  <l>By baſe life now brought low, a filthy thing.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>Look on murdering <hi>Cain,</hi> idolatrous <hi>Ahab,</hi> painted <hi>Jezabel,</hi> rebellious <hi>Abſalom,</hi> and treacherous <hi>Judas,</hi> and their names ſtink in the noſtrila of men. Their me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory carrieth ſuch an <hi>Odium</hi> with it, as all deteſt, and caſt it forth as dung in the ſtreets. Drunken <hi>Tiberius Nero</hi> hath the deſerved Epithete of <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iberius Mero;</hi> And another Emperor this, <hi>Non homo ſed por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:104571:7"/>Sardinapalus erat: Sardinapalus</hi> was no man but a Swine. <hi>Caligula</hi> that Monſter of Nature, who kept a Common Stewa for both Sexes to fill his coffers, a Wretch ſo avaritious, that he would ſpread himſelf over his treaſure; was ſtab'd by his own Servants with this watch-word, <hi>Hoc age,</hi> minde this only. His name is ſo deteſtable, that all ſpit at it, but once mentioned. And can our beaſtly Drunkards and Epicures, who make their belly their Gods, can our goatiſh Adulterers defile their bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, which are Gods temples, making them members of an Harlot; and can our covetous muck-worms, that eat the people of God as men eat bread, think to eſcape? No an <hi>odium</hi> will be upon their names to perpetuity, and an O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cean of waters ſhall never waſh away their ſtains. Wherefore as <hi>David</hi> ſaid to <hi>Ahimelech,</hi> of the ſword of <hi>Goliah;</hi> There is none like that, give it me. 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 21 29. So there is nothing com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parable to a godly and vertnous life to preſerve a good name. It is like the Cherubims and flaming ſword, which turneth every way, to keep the way of
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:104571:7"/>this tree of life. <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.24. This is that <hi>Rizpah,</hi> that ſuffereth neither the birds of the air to reſt on them by day, nor the beaſt of the field by night to prey upon them. 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 21.10. But what if innocencie it ſelf and fair vertue can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſtop the madneſſe of the people? Suppoſe that ſome ſons of <hi>Belial,</hi> for all this, will be blotting thy fair coppy, and ſeek to impair thy integrity? Care not for it; <hi>Ne hili aeſtima,</hi> weigh it not the black of a Bean: and ſay with <hi>S. Paul,</hi> But with me it is a very ſmall thing that I ſhould be judged of you, or of mans judgement. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.3. I would conclude the point, but that I muſt ſay ſomething of our credulous men, whoſe ears are open to every tale, thoſe common ſhores that receive all waters and kennels to run through them. <hi>Epicarmus</hi> was wont to ſay; <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mento diffidere,</hi> be not too credulous. For it is moſt true; If there were no tale-hearer, there would be no tale-hearer. And verily as the Devil ſitteth on the tongue of the one, ſo be ſitteth on the car of the other. And I cannot tell which of the two is worſe. Theſe,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:104571:8"/>as thief and receiver are relatives, and like Addition in Arithmetick, caſt up the particulars, and both make but one groſs Sum. I may ſay of theſe Youths, as one ſometime of the Popes Legate, <hi>Sic bacchinantur in Provinciis, &amp;c.</hi> They ſo revel it in the Provinces, and make ſuch havock where they come; as if the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil were let looſe of God to ſcourge hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Church. We uſe to ſay, and it is very true; <hi>Plus gula, quam gladio.</hi> More men are ſlain by the throat, meaning by ſurfets and drunkenneſſe, then by the ſword. Even ſo more are murdered in their good names, by thoſe that ſpeak through their throat by way of defa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of good men, then ſuch as fall by the ſword. It is the part of a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian to conſtrue all in the beter ſenſe, and to have a candid conſtruction of reports; For to believe all ſpoken to thee in the detraction of thy brother, may bring an innocent man into a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munire, and cauſe thee to infringe the Laws both of nature and religion. How did <hi>David</hi> though one after Gods own heart, by too much hearkning to the falſ ſuggeſtion of flattering <hi>Ziba,</hi> wrong
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:104571:8"/>a good man, even <hi>Mephiboſheth;</hi> and the only ſon of his dear friend, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 16.4. This took away <hi>Naboths</hi> vineyard, and his life, 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 21.13. <hi>Tertullus</hi> the O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rator thought this the beſt way to crack the credit of S. <hi>Paul,</hi> and like water to ſpill it on the ground, not to be gather<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed up, <hi>Acts</hi> 24.5, 6, &amp;c. <hi>Joſeph</hi> the chaft, by his wanton Miſtreſſes falſ accuſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, was caſt into priſon, <hi>Gen.</hi> 39.20. <hi>Suſanna,</hi> that honeſt and good ſoul, had almoſt loſt her life too, by this murder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing peece; had not Gods mercy oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunely intervened to the ſaving of his handmaid. What ſhould I ſay more? Our bleſſed Lord himſelf had this Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non ſhot at him; the peece goeth off, but being foul, breaketh and flyeth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout their ears who firſt gave <hi>fire</hi> to it, <hi>Luke</hi> 23.2. <hi>Mark</hi> 15.3. <hi>Matth.</hi> 27.12. There are three things amiable in the ſight of God and men: <hi>Concordia fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trum, amicitia propinquorum, &amp; vir &amp; uxor inter ſe convenientes;</hi> Concord of bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, friendſhip of neighbours, and a man and his wife agreeing together. And now what putteth theſe inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments out of tune but the foul hand
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:104571:9"/>of Calumny? Who cauſeth a ſeparation of theſe three lovely pairs but falf tales and ſuggeſtions? Nothing breaketh the peace more then this. Oh, what confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, what ſad troubles have followed them! Such turbulent ſpirits have been raiſed in one hour, as could ſcarce be layed in many years after. Theſe bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows have kindled ſuch a fire as no wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters have been able to quench it. So horrid and deplorable hath been the ſad conſequence of the ready reception of a ſlaunder; as I may ſay of him, and the author of it, as (<hi>Jacob</hi> of <hi>Simeon</hi> and <hi>Levi</hi>) they are brethren, inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental of cruelty are in their habitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,<hi>Gen.</hi> 49.5. <note n="d" place="margin">Simile.</note> In a ſtorm the ſhip is toſſed to and fro, reeleth like a drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken man; one while it mounts as high as heaven, and then falls as low as hell; the lightnings flaſh on their faces, the proud waves beat upon them, and fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful darkneſſe like a black mantle, begirt the trembling marriners; now they are at their wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s end, and<note n="e" place="margin">Acts 27.20.</note> all hope that they ſhall be ſaved is taken away; Thus is it, when the fire of contention is blown up by the breath of ſuch, who
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:104571:9"/>go from houſe to houſe to carry tales; and it kindles the more into flame, when it meets with combuſtable matter, a facil diſpoſition, an ear open to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive it. When this Euroclydon once riſeth; (unleſſe the Lord) whom the winds and ſea obey, in mercy intervene, the tempeſt will riſe ſo high, as nothing but miſerable, ſhip wrack can be expect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. Hear I pray all of you whom it may concern, what direction <hi>Titus</hi> hath from the Apoſtle, <hi>Titus</hi> 3.2. To ſpeak evil of no man, to be no brawlers, but gentle, ſhewing all meekneſſe unto all men. This thing was ſo hateful to <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid,</hi> that he thus ſpeaks of it, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 101.5. Whoſo privily ſlaundereth his neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, him will I cut off, Mark but this dilewma; I ſuppoſe it will nonplus the beſt Sophiſter.<note place="margin">Matth. 7.12.</note> Therefore all things whatſoever ye would that men ſhould do to you, do you even ſo to them:<note place="margin">Luk. 6.31.</note> for this is the law and the prophets. Now wouldſt thou have any ſlaunder and backbite thee? No. Thou art then an unreaſonable man; <hi>Non compos mentis,</hi> to do that unto another, which thou abhorreſt to have done unto thy ſelf.
<gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:104571:10"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:104571:10"/>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:104571:11"/>I ſhould bite my tongue firſt, before I would perpetrate a ſin ſo unworthy, ſo beneath a Chriſtian, I may ſay a man. For if thy tongue be employed in this particular, and runs on this errand;<note n="f" place="margin">James 3.6.</note> It is a ſire, a world of iniquity: ſo is the tongue amongſt our members, that it defileth the whole body, and ſetteth on fire the courſe of nature, and it is ſet on fire of hell. Bluſh then (for ſhame) if thou beeſt guilty this way, and ſay with <hi>Pharaohs</hi> Butler,<note n="g" place="margin">Gen: 41.9.</note> I do remember my faults this day. And with holy <hi>Job,</hi> from a ſorrowful and penitent heart, ſweetly warble forth (as he in another ſenſe) Wherefore I abhor my ſelf, and repent in duſt and aſhes, <hi>Job.</hi> 42.6. If this will not ſerve, let them know they are murderers, and children of the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil, <hi>John</hi> 8.44. Ye are of your father the devil, and the luſts of your father ye will do; he was a murderer from the beginning, and abode not in the truth becauſe there is no truth in him. When he ſpeaketh a lye, he ſpeaketh of his own: for he is a lyar and the father of it. And if they be murderers; then their ſin cryeth to heaven for vengeance.
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:104571:11"/>Among the four capitall, or (if you pleaſe) Cardinal vices that cry, this is ſet in the front,<note n="h" place="margin">Clami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tani ad coe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum vex ſangumis, vox Sodo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rum, Vox op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſorum, merces de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenta la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borum.</note>
               <hi>Vix ſanguinis,</hi> the voice of blood. <hi>Gen.</hi> 4.10. the voice o thy brothers blood cryeth unto me from the ground. And not only ſo; but they are excluded the heavenly Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem, no unclean thing can enter there,<note n="i" place="margin">Revel. 22.15.</note> For without are dogs, and Sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerers, and whoremongers, and murde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers; and idolators, and (in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ere) whoſoever love h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and maketh a lye. And ſo leaving them to ſtand or fall to their own Maſters, I come to the people; and now hear what they think of due Saviour.</p>
            <p>Some ſay that thou art <hi>John</hi> the <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptiſt;</hi> ſome <hi>Elias,</hi> and o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hers <hi>Jeremias,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Second ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation.</note> or one of the prophets. Hence I obſerve, That the vulgar, concerning Chriſt, and other matters of faith, are often various and unſatisfied: they hold and believe that which is not ſound and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thodox. Like the blinde man in the Goſpel, they diſcern not aright; as he ſaw men like trees. How many have we who know not what God, what Chriſt or what faith is. In this particular they
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:104571:12"/>are as mute as fiſhes, and as the horſe and mule that have no underſtanding. Either they are ignorant of what true religion is, or they ſtand in doubt of it, and make a queſtion, whether there be any ſuch thing or no. Witneſſe, our many ſects and opinioniſts that ſwarm every where; namely, our blaſphemous Quaker, away with ſuch a fellow from the earth. Our Simpleton Seeker (of a needle in a bottle of hay) Our ignorant Leveller, that would beget a parity a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong men, which is impoſſible,<note n="k" place="margin">Mark. 14</note> For the poor ye have always with you; Our dipping Anabaptiſt, <hi>verberibus magis quam verbis,</hi> authority muſt cudgel it out of him, for diſputes boot not. What ſhould I ſpeak of Judaiſm, Turciſm, Heathen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſm, Atheiſm, &amp;c. In ſuch diverſity of opinions what ſhall we determine? Shall we bear them? ſhall we commend them? or ſhall we deteſt them?<note n="l" place="margin">Laudare mon poſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus, dete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtari d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus, ferre cogimur. <hi>Dierec. Annal.</hi>
               </note> Praiſe them we cannot, we ought to abhor them, we are forced to ſuffer them. Here is all our Comfort, the harveſt will one day day come, when the wheat ſhall be put into the granary of Heaven, and the tares caſt into the fire.</p>
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:104571:12"/>
            <p>In the interim, though we live by them, let us not live with them. By any means, avoid converſing, though we cannot commercing with them altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther;<note n="m" place="margin">1 Cor. 5.10</note> for then muſt ye needs go out of the world. But above all, make not your ſelves one with them by marriage, leſt ye propagate a mungrel and mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrous generation. This was the ſin of the old world; when<note n="n" place="margin">Gen. 6.2.</note> the Sons of God ſaw the daughters of men that they were fair, they took them wives of all that they choſe. <hi>Modo forma placuiſſet,</hi> Beauty alone pleas'd them, as <hi>Tremel.</hi> upon the Text. So the joyn bodies and hearts together, and ten to one but Religion hazards a final divorce. Hear what a father of the Church ſaith,<note n="o" place="margin">Neque in confuſione Paganorum, neque in pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gamentis haereticorum, neque in languore ſchiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maticorum, neque in coe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citate Judaeorum quaeren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da eſt religio, &amp;c.</note> Religion is to be ſought, neither in the confuſion of Pagans, neither in the filth of Heretiques, nor in the languour of Schiſmaticks, nor in the blindneſſe of the Jews; but with thoſe alone who are called Orthodox Chriſtians,<note place="margin">Aug. lib. de verit. Rel. Cap. 5.</note> and Catholique, that is to ſay, ſuch as are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainers
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:104571:13"/>of integrity, and thoſe which follow warrantable wayes. But let me (beloved) hit the nail on the head. If ever thou or I deſire to finde ſure foot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, we muſt do this one thing; even proſtrate our ſelves at the feet of Chriſt, and take what drops from his mouth; for God is true, and all men are lyars. I ſay, let us meekly attend his ſacred Word, it is the only rule we muſt walk by. This is <hi>Lucerna qua fur deprehendi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur,</hi> as a Father ſaith, The light by which the thief is deſcried. I mean the great thief of all, Sathan; and the little ones, the wicked of the wold, ſeduced of both ſexes; who deceive and are deceived, like thoſe enemies of the truth, of whom S. <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaks, that creep into houſes, and lead captive ſilly women, laden with ſins, led away with divers luſts, ever learning, and never able to come to the knowledge of the truth, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3 6 7. Now, as <hi>Jannes</hi> and <hi>Jambres</hi> withſtood <hi>Moſes,</hi> ſo do theſe alſo reſiſt the truth: men of corrupt mindes, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probate concerning the faith, verſe 8. This light concerns us much then in the deſcrying of theſe thieves. The Word
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:104571:13"/>is to a Chriſtian, as the Card and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſs is to a Marriner, it makes him ſail ſafely through the ſea of this world; whereas without it, millions are caſt away. Wherefore as our Saviour ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniſheth; Search the Scriptures, for in them you think to have everlaſting life. Yet beware, ſo ſearch them, that you miſtake them not; for otherwiſe I may ſay again, as Chriſt to them of old, Ye do erre not knowing the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures. They were big words which <hi>Julius Ceſar</hi> ſpake, and me thinks, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what hyperbolical, more cry then wool, though, I confeſſe, he was a fortunate and valiant man;<note n="p" place="margin">Veni vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>di, vici.</note> I came, ſad he, to the enemy, and lookt upon them, and conquer'd them. But is is a greater task (my brethren) upon the firſt ſight to conquor the ſence of the Scriptures; where in ſome places the waters are ſo deep, that an Elephant may not only ſwim, but drown. Whoſoever have the ſaving knowledge of the Word, it is by divine diſpenſation,<note n="q" place="margin">Manns in nube.</note> the good hand of Providence is upon him. A man may read and hear much, and all to little purpoſe, if the Star of Gods Spirit ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:104571:14"/>not, and ſo direct him to Chriſt. Then opened he their underſtanding, that they might underſtand the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures, <hi>Luk.</hi> 23.45. Had not the Lord ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the heart of <hi>Lydia</hi> to give attention, <hi>Pauls</hi> oratory had done her little good, <hi>Act,</hi> 16.14. When <hi>Philip</hi> ſaid to the Eunuch; Underſtandeſt thou what thou readeſt? How can I, ſaid he, except ſome man ſhould guide me? <hi>Acts</hi> 8.30, 31. The men alone behinde the cloath make the pupets move. And Almighty God only can and muſt illuminate our underſtandings, and anoint our eyes with eye-ſalve, that we may ſee, <hi>Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lat.</hi> 3.18.</p>
            <p>And here, in the next place, I pray obſerve, how difficult a thing it is to leave a cuſtom once taken up.<note n="r" place="margin">Pravus uſus vix aboletur. <hi>Iſid. lib. 1. Soliloq.</hi>
               </note> A wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed habit is hardly left off. Waſh a black Moor, and the ſigne is <hi>Labour in vain.</hi> Cuſtom in any thing is a ſecond nature, and it clings ſo eloſe to a man, as if it were born with him, and he ſucked it from his mothers breaſt. It is like the heart within him, although it is not the firſt thing that liveth, yet it is the laſt that dyeth.<note place="margin">ultimum moriens.</note> See it verefied in the Jews
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:104571:14"/>in my Text. Some think Chriſt to be <hi>John</hi> the <hi>Baptiſt,</hi> ſome <hi>Elias, Jeremias,</hi> or one of the prophets. And all out of an old cuſtom and miſtake, that they could not give a right definition of him. It was not the firſt time that <hi>Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeph</hi> ſwore by the life of <hi>Pharaoh</hi> when he had it ſo ready in his mouth. The Ephraimites could not pronounce <hi>Shib<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boleth,</hi> but ſay <hi>Sibboleth, Judg.</hi> 12.6<note n="ſ" place="margin">Quo ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mel imbut a recens ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vabit odo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rom Teſta diu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Horat.</hi>
               </note> A veſſel will ſavour of that liquour, it laſt received, and it will taſte of it a long time after. As for example; A common drunkard ſeldom turneth ſo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ber man, and a deſperate ſwearer will ever have an oath in his mouth. Mark an unclean perſon, his words will be obſcene and ſcurrilous; not a ſyllable cometh from him that adminiſtreth grace to the hearers. A covetous muck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worm alwayes ſavours of earth; and with <hi>Eſau,</hi> his ſmell is the ſmell of a field, as <hi>Iſaac</hi> ſaid to <hi>Jacob,</hi> taking him for <hi>Eſau, Gen.</hi> 27.27 Take him at his Oriſons, or private devotions (which you ſhall ſeldom do) and though he make long prayers, yet with the Scribes and Phariſees, it is to devour widows
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:104571:15"/>houſes. The world is ever his center, and this Dor, fly he never ſo long, end<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth his flight on a dunghil. Take him in the Church, and if his eyes be intent upon the Preacher, his thoughts are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trograde, and with the Devil are going to and fro in the earth, and walking up and down in it, <hi>Job.</hi> 1.7. See this confirmd in our bloody <hi>Nimrods,</hi> thoſe mighty hunters before the Lord; who with <hi>Caligula</hi> are <hi>Lutum ſanguine mace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratum,</hi> a lump of clay ſoaked in blood; they are accuſtomed to murther, as the killing of a man is no more to them then the killing of a flea, although it be a ſin ſo hainous, that it cryeth to heaven for vengeance, <hi>Gen.</hi> 4.10. It is recorded of a Roman Emperour, who when he was alone, ſpent his time in pricking of flyes with his penknife, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomuch, when one asked who was with the Emperour, anſwer was wittily re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned, <hi>Nemuſca quidem:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Sueton.</note> Not so much truly as a flye. <hi>Caligula,</hi> whom I men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned before, like an incarnate Devil, brake out into theſe words;<note n="t" place="margin">
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>tinam populus Romanus unum cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vicem ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beret.</note> I could wiſh the people of Rome had but one neck, that he might cut them of at once.
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:104571:15"/>And the reaſon is, Cuſtom in ſinning taketh away the ſence and feeling of ſin. Philoſophers ſay, <hi>Elementum aquae ſuo loco non ponderat;</hi> The element of wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in its proper place is not heavy. As for example, Let a man dive to the bottom of a river, and he cometh up with eaſe; yet let the ſame man take but a bucket and fill it with water, and he will finde the carrlage ponderous and troubleſom. Thus is it in once accuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to ſin: whilſt he is in that element (as I may ſo ſpeak) though whole ſeas of impiety cover him, he is inſenſible of the burthen; but if one, by divine aſſistance, he cometh out through a ſence of his deplorable condition; he will then ſay with <hi>David,</hi> Mine iniquities are gone over my head as an heavy burthen, they are to heavy for me. <hi>Pſalm</hi> 38.4. What ſhould we do then in this caſe? what remedy for this ſore? Only, <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veat emptor;</hi> beware how thou makeſt thy bargain with Sin. The foreman in the ſhop is Sathan, and he cannot away with returns of his bad ware. What is that to us, ſee thou to that, ſaid the chief prieſts and elders to <hi>Judas</hi> after he
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:104571:16"/>had betrayed his Maſter, and was trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled in conſcience, <hi>Matth.</hi> 27.4. Thou wilt one day ſay to the Devil and thy ſins, as <hi>Job</hi> ſometime to his Friends, Miſerable comforters are you all. Sin is like a ſtorm at ſea, firſt there are <hi>leves undae,</hi> ſmall waves, after that <hi>majora vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumina,</hi> greater volumes of water; and at laſt <hi>fluctus ad coelum,</hi> ſurges mounting up to heaven. The firſt committing of ſin is not ſo dangerous as a frequent and common perpetration. A man may waſh himſelf nigh the ſhore, yea, he may go ſo far as he can well wade, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out danger; but if he once ſtep beyond his depth, it muſt be a hand of provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence if he be ſaved. And we ſhould the rather be wary, in regard of the proneneſs of our nature to ſin: All the imaginations of our hearts are only evil continually, <hi>Gen.</hi> 6. And without grace, it is as natural for us to ſin, as for ponderous things to tend down<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards. Can we then be too careful to fall into that, whereto we have ſo facil, and genuine a diſpoſition, ſo innate and inbred faculty. The dogs of Aegypt drink of the river Nilus as they run for fear of
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:104571:16"/>a Crocadile; and ſhall we lye down and drink our fill of ſin, when that Croca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dile Sathan is ready to devour us: and eſpecially when it is a work of power to reclaim us? God forbid. To con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude the point; Concerning the opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions in my Text, and the fond con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceits which the people through cuſtom and uſe had of Chriſt; let us waſh our hands of them, and cordially pray, <hi>From all Sedition and privie conſpiracy, from all falſe doctrine and hereſy, from hardneſſe of heart, and contempt of thy Word and Commandment, Good Lord deliver us.</hi> In the interim, let us be conſtant to our principles, and like oaks, withſtand all windes of contrary tenents, which are diſconſonant to the analogie of faith. And let us always remember that of S. <hi>Paul,</hi> For there muſt be alſo hereſies among you, that they which are ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved may be made manifeſt among you, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.19. And <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.14. That we henceforth be no more chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren toſſed to and fro, and carried a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout with every winde of doctrine, by the ſlight of men, and cunning crafti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, whereby they lye in wait to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive.
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:104571:17"/>And ſo I come to the confeſſion of the Apoſtles in the name and perſon of <hi>Peter.</hi> verſ. 15, 16.</p>
            <p>He ſaith unto them,<note place="margin">The Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion.</note>, but whom ſay ye that I am; And <hi>Simon Peter</hi> anſwered and ſaid, Thou art Chriſt the Son of the living God. This confeſſion or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſponſion we have, firſt, from the princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple efficient cauſe, which was S. <hi>Peter.</hi> And it is amplified from the adjunct his proper name, <hi>Simon,</hi> and by his ſirname <hi>Peter;</hi> which ſignifieth a rock, as <hi>Mark</hi> 3.16 And <hi>Simon</hi> he ſirnamed <hi>Peter.</hi> So <hi>Luke</hi> 6.14. <hi>Simon</hi> whom he alſo named <hi>Peter.</hi> And <hi>Cephas</hi> in the Hebrew, (or as the Learned ſay) rather in the Sy<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iack tongue is all one with <hi>Peter</hi> in the Greek, and ſignifieth a rock or ſtone. Now in that <hi>Peter</hi> is the mouth of the reſt of the Apoſtles, and their ſpoakſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, it was not becauſe he thought himſelf the chief of his brethren; no, he never dreamed any ſuch thing,<note n="u" place="margin">Quia ardore Chriſti praecipou ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens, &amp; ad facien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum, &amp; ad reſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dendum paratiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus erat. <hi>Cyrill. lib. 12. in Johan.</hi>
               </note> neither was he taken with that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ectick fever, but as <hi>Cyril</hi> hath it, Becauſe being more fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent in the love of Chriſt, he was moſt ready to make and give an anſwer.</p>
            <pb n="33" facs="tcp:104571:17"/>
            <p>Again, in that he alone made anſwer, in the name of the reſt of the Apoſtles. For,<note n="x" place="margin">Fides catholica una eſt ubicunque &amp; apud quoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cunque fie. Ideo conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niens fuit confeſſionem ejus per unum fieri, liee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> illu eſſet fides multorum. <hi>Toſtar ſuper locum, Queſt. 56.</hi>
               </note> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever and with whomſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver it is found. It was there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſit the Confeſſion of Chriſt to be made by one, although it were the belief of many. To confirm the ſame, we have the like Confeſſion, <hi>John</hi> 6.69. Where though Saint <hi>Peter</hi> ſpeaks only, yet he delivereth it in the plural number. And we believe and are ſure, that thou art that Chriſt the Son of the living God. Secondly here is the form of the confeſſion; Thou art are Chriſt the Son of the living God. Which confeſſion though it be in few words, the matter is high and ſublime; for in it is contained that great myſtery of God made man; and the perſon and office of our Saviour. Firſt, Chriſt is God coequal and coeſſential with the Father and the Holy Ghoſt. To this end he is called, The only begotten of the Father, <hi>John</hi> 1.14. Thus is he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten of the eſſence of his Father from
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:104571:18"/>all eternity, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 2.7. Thou art my Son, this day have I begotten thee. And the Text, Thou art Chriſt the Son of the living God. He is ſaid to be the Living God<note n="y" place="margin">Secundum ſupereminen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiam, qua ſuperemines om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nibus habe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tibus vitam, quemad modum ſolus ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bet immortalitatem. <hi>Orig.</hi>
               </note> according to his Supereminency, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in he is above all living, as one that hath only immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tality, and is the fountain of life. So S. <hi>John</hi> Chap. 14.6. I am the way, the truth, and the life. And he is called the living God alſo,<note n="z" place="margin">Ad comparationem co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum deorum qui putantur dii, ſed mortui ſunt; Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turnum dico, Jovem, Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerem, &amp; coetera idolorum portenta. <hi>Hier.</hi>
               </note> in compariſon of thoſe gods, who are thought to be gods, but are all dead, I ſay <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn, Jupiter</hi> and <hi>Venus,</hi> and the other forms of idols. S. <hi>Paul Heb.</hi> 1.3. hath it—Who being the brightneſſe of his glory, and the expreſſe image of his perſon. But to put all out of doubt, the Apoſtle hath this dilemma, <hi>Coloſ</hi> 1.16. For by him were all things crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted that are in Heaven, and that are in earth, viſible and inviſible, whether they be thrones, or dominions, or principalities, or powers, all things wers created by him and for him. Saint
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:104571:18"/>
               <hi>John</hi> ſaith 1 <hi>John</hi> 5.20. This is the true God and eternal life. And <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.5. Who is over all God bleſſed for ever, Amen.</p>
            <p>Secondly, As our Saviour is true God, ſo likewiſe he is true man, of the ſubſtance of his Mother, born in the world. This is manifeſt by his own words, verſ. 13. Whom do men ſay that I the Son of man am? To this purpoſe he hath the plain Epithete of Man given him, <hi>Luke</hi> 23.47. Now when the Centurion ſaw what was done, he glorified God, ſaying; Certainly this was a righteous man. And the Apoſtle, 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.5. For there is one God, and one Mediatour between God and men, the man Chriſt Jeſus. Wherefore he is called the ſon of <hi>Mary, Matth.</hi> 1.16. The ſeed of the woman. <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.15. The ſeed of <hi>Abraham, Heb.</hi> 2.16. Born of a woman, <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.4. Yet notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, though he be God and man, he is not two, but one Chriſt. Accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to <hi>Athanaſius</hi> his Creed. One, not by Converſion of the Godhead into fleſh, but by taking the manhood into God; one altogether, not by confuſion
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:104571:19"/>of Subſtance, but by unity of Perſon; For as the reaſonable ſoul and fleſh is one man; ſo God and man is one Chriſt. To this purpoſe the Apoſtle ſaith, there is one Lord Jeſus Chriſt, 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 8.6. And one Mediatour be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween God and men, 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.5. Thus we ſee he is but one Chriſt. In the next place we have his office expreſſed in the word, Chriſt. Thou art Chriſt, &amp;c. which word ſignifieth anointed. For whereas Kings, Prieſts, and Prophets, were uſually anointed in the Old Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament upon their inauguration, <hi>Exod.</hi> 29.7.1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 16.13. Hence they are cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the Lords anointed, <hi>Eſay</hi> 48.1. So likewiſe was Chriſt anointed, not with any external oil, but with the Holy Ghoſt, into a Kingly, Prophetick, and Prieſtly office, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 45.8. <hi>John</hi> 3.34. <hi>Acts</hi> 10.38. Firſt, he was anointed a Prophet to make known the will of his heavenly Father concerning our redem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption; <hi>John</hi> 1.10. No man hath ſeen God at any time, the only begotten Son which is in the boſom of the Father, he hath declared him. And in the next place, that he might appoint us the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:104571:19"/>of the-Word, and the uſe of the Sacraments; that by theſe, as (by in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments) he might work effectually in his Church, as <hi>Mark</hi> 16 15.16. Go ye into all the world, and preach the Goſpel to every creature; He that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieveth and is baptized, ſhall be ſaved; but he that believeth not ſhall be damn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. Secondly, he was anointed a Prieſt, that he might offer himſelf on the Croſs for us, and by the ſacrifice of his own body, redeem us from our moſt ſad and deplorable condition in the loins of our firſt parents; and that he might ever intercede for us to his Father. For by one offering he hath perfected for even them that are ſanctified, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.14. and chap. 9.24. For Chriſt is not aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded into the holy places made with hands, which are the figures of the true, but into heaven it ſelf, now to appear in the preſence of God for us: And <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.34. Who is he that condemneth? it is Chriſt that died; yea rather that is riſen again, who is even at the right hand of God, who alſo maketh inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion for us. Thirdly, he was anoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed a King that he might rule and govern
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:104571:20"/>us by the Scepter of his power; that is, that he might preſerve and defend us both from our corporal and ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual enemies; to wit, the Devil, Sin, Death, Hell, and this wicked World. Wherefore the Prophet thus ſpeaketh, Rejoyce greatly O daughter of Zion, ſhout O daughter of Jeruſalem; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold thy King cometh unto thee, he is juſt, and having ſalvation, &amp;c. <hi>Zach.</hi> 9.9. And the Evangeliſt; Then ſhall the king ſay unto them on his right hand, Come ye bleſſed of my Father, inherit the kingdom prepared for you from the foundation of the world, <hi>Matth.</hi> 25.34</p>
            <p>From this Confeſſion of <hi>Peter</hi> we may learn what is the duty of every Chriſtian man; even this, freely to give an account of his faith. According to that of the Apoſtle, But ſanctiſte the Lord God in your hearts, and be ready alwayes to give an anſwer to every man that asketh you a reaſon of the hope that is in you with meek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and fear, I <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.15. And to take off all excuſe in this particular, our Saviour himſelf ſaith, Whoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever therefore ſhall confeſſe me before
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:104571:20"/>men, him will I confeſſe alſo before my Father which is in heaven, <hi>Matth.</hi> 10.32. Holy <hi>David</hi> maketh it a fruit of faith, <hi>Pſalm</hi> 116.10. I believed therefore have ſpoken.<note n="a" place="margin">Veritas &amp; creden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da, &amp; laquenda.</note> The truth (ſaith <hi>Proſper</hi>) is to be believed, and ſpoken. Confeſſion is of a high conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence, and concerns Chriſtains more then they think of. This I believe wrings many a profeſſor by the noſe, and toucheth (as we ſay) their c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ppy hold. How many have we that dare not confeſſe the truth openly for fear of men. Theſe are cowardly Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, who when they ſhould fight, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take them to their heels. Some will make a fair flouriſh for a time; they will take up the Cudgels with much ſeeming Confidence: but when any cometh to play with them, they pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently lay them down. Such a one was S. <hi>Peter,</hi> Hear his high words; Though all ſhould be offended becauſe of thee, yet will I never be offended. And further, Though I ſhould die with thee, yet will I not deny thee, <hi>Matth.</hi> 26.33.35. but look upon him a while after, and then, <hi>quantum mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatus
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:104571:21"/>ab illo,</hi> one would not take him to be the ſame man: How are the chariot wheels of his reſolution ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken off, ſo that he drives heavily. Mark him I pray; I know not what thou ſayeſt; and again, with and oath in his mouth; I do not know the man. And to make him ſuperlative, he falls more baſely; begins to curſe and to ſwear, ſaying; I know not the man, verſ. 70.72.74. Who would have taken <hi>Spira</hi> otherwiſe then a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitian once; but miſerable man, when he was urged to ſubſcribe, or elſe loſe all, and incurre the Popes diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſure ſtraightwayes makes ſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wrack of faith and a good conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence; and after this, by God his di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine juſtice, dieth in horrible deſpair. Is not this an Epidemical diſeaſe? What Thraſonian brags will our mun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grel profeſſours make in times of peace and proſperity? Who better Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans now then they? whilſt this calm laſts, it is a hard matter to finde out the true Mother: a baſe hypocriticall Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſee can ſcarce be diſcerned from a <hi>Nathaneel,</hi> a true Iſraelite indeed, in
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:104571:21"/>whom there is no guile: but let one ſtorm ariſe; let the Sabeans take a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way their oxen, and their aſſes, or the Chaldeans fall upon their camels; or let a priſon be threatned them; the leaſt guſt of adverſity blow upon them, and as Sathan falſly ſaid of <hi>Job,</hi> it may truly be ſaid of them, they will curſe God to his face. Moſt ſad ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience we have had of this in all ages, and the Apoſtacy of our times is a ſufficient teſt and proof of it. Confeſſe we then the truth, maugre the menaces and threats of wicked men. Let this never be forgotten of us. But whoſoever ſhall deny me before men, him will I alſo deny before my Father which is in heaven, <hi>Matth.</hi> 10.33. And worthy is that of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle to be writ in the tables of our hearts, <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.9, 10. That if thou ſhalt confeſſe with my mouth the Lord Jeſus, and ſhalt believe in thine heart, that God hath raiſed him from the dead, thou ſhalt be ſaved. For with the heart man believeth unto righteouſneſſe, and with the mouth Confeſſion is made unto Salvation.
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:104571:22"/>Secondly, this more eſpecially con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns the Miniſters of God his word: they of all other muſt freely deliver the truth.<note n="b" place="margin">Nihil in ſacerdote tam periculoſum apud Deuw, tam iurpe apud homine<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, quam quod ſentiat veri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catem non libere, pronun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eiare. <hi>Ambr.</hi>
               </note> Nothing in a Miniſter is ſo dangerous with a God, and baſe with men, then not to ſpeak that freely which he thinketh to be truth.</p>
            <p>I was ſpoken like a prophet: As the Lord liveth, what the Lord ſaith unto me, that will I ſpeak, 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 22.14. And no leſſe noble was it ſaid by <hi>Nehemiah;</hi> Should ſuch a man as I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> flee, chap. 6.11; Theſe are the pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars of the Church, if they fall, down cometh the whole fabrick. It is a ſhame to ſee a man of God turn tail, for him to deny the truth is mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrous, who will truſt that ſheepheard, or (rather that thief) who ſeeing the wolf coming, leaveth the ſheep and flyeth, <hi>John</hi> 16.12. He that ſitteth as the ſtern muſt not leave it for every ſtorm, leſt he hazardeth the whole veſſel, and ſo commit the Marriners to the mercy of the ſeas. Look to this ye Embaſſadours of the moſt high God,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:104571:22"/>and betray not through your cowar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſe thoſe ſouls comitted to your charge. What more worthy of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>memoration, then that of he Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, who when they were put into the common priſon for preaching in the name of Chriſt; preſently they entred into the Temple early in the morning, and taught, ſaying; We ought to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey God rather than men; and boldly told them to their faces; The God of our fathers raiſed up Jeſus, whom ye ſlew and hanged on a tree; him hath God exalted with his right hand to be a prince and a Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour, for to give repentance to Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael and forgiveneſſe of ſins, <hi>Acts</hi> 5. 18.21.29.30.31. Who can but ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mire at the Conſtancy and brave ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of <hi>Martin Luther,</hi> who when he was by ſome of his friends diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded from going to Wormes, made this anſwer, If every tyle of each houſe was a devil, yet would I go thither. O noble ſoul, thy name will be had in remembrance to thy immortall praiſe. Let my counſel be accepted of you, my dear brethren of the Clergie;
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:104571:23"/>Yea let the wiſe mans counſell be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted of you;<note n="c" place="margin">Prov. 19.10.</note> Buy the truth, and ſell it not. Let no panick fear poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſe you when you ſhould proclaim the glad tidings of the goſpel, and preach ſalvation through the merit of Chriſt. He is the Son of the living God (ſaith my Text) who will own you his Champions, and reward you with a crown of immortality, if ye be conſtant. What i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the world hate you for it; Take this Cordial, Be of good comfort, I have overcome the world ſaid your great Maſter once. And if God be for us, who can be againſt us? <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.31. Take this for all, even from him who is Alpha and Omega, the firſt and the laſt, he that liveth and was dead, and hath the keyes of hell and of death. Fear none of thoſe things which thou ſhalt ſuffer; behold the devil ſhall caſt ſome of you into priſon that ye may be tryed, and ye ſhall have tribulation ten dayes; be thou faithful unto death, and I will give thee a crown of life, <hi>Rev.</hi> 2.10. At for thoſe Milk-ſops, thoſe fearful watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, ambodexters, and trencher Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lains,
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:104571:23"/>who for ſiniſter ends ſpeak what God never put into their mouths, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the plain text of Scripture, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nying the Lord that bought them, and ſo making ſhipwrack of faith and a good conſcience, to the hazarding of many thouſand ſouls; Good God give them repentance to the acknowledging of the truth: If not, the wiſh of the Apoſtle, to all you that fear God, ſhall be mine; I would they were even cut off that trouble you. <hi>Amen. Gal.</hi> 5.12.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
